<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A True and most exact relation of the taking of the goodly ship called the Saint Esprit, belonging vnto the French king which was built in Holland, and furnished with 54 peeces of great ordnance, was surprised on the 28 day of September, by Sir Sackeuill Treuer, Knight, and since brought by him vnto Harwich in Essex ; likewise the proceedings of the Duke of Buckingham his Grace, in the Isle of Ree ... with many other particulars / published by authority.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1627</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13958</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24268.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2936</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">29527389</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 29527389</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27994</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13958)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27994)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1859:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A True and most exact relation of the taking of the goodly ship called the Saint Esprit, belonging vnto the French king which was built in Holland, and furnished with 54 peeces of great ordnance, was surprised on the 28 day of September, by Sir Sackeuill Treuer, Knight, and since brought by him vnto Harwich in Essex ; likewise the proceedings of the Duke of Buckingham his Grace, in the Isle of Ree ... with many other particulars / published by authority.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 11 p., 1 leaf of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.M. for Thomas Walkley, and are to be sold at his shop at the Signe of the Eagle and Childe in Britaines Burse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1627.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trevor, Sackvill, --  Sir, fl. 1604.</term>
               <term>Saint Esprit (Ship)</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History, Naval --  Stuarts, 1603-1714.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:27994:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27994:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>ships and smiling fish scene</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27994:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27994:2"/>
            <p>A TRVE AND MOST Exact Relation of the taking of the goodly Ship called the <hi>Saint Eſprit,</hi> belonging vnto the <hi>French</hi> King, which was built in <hi>Holland,</hi> and furniſhed with 54. Peeces of great Ordnance was ſurpriſed on the 28. day of <hi>September,</hi> by Sir <hi>Sackeuill Treuer</hi> Knight, and ſince brought ouer by him vnto <hi>Harwich in</hi> ESSEX.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Likewiſe,</hi> The Proceedings of the Duke of <hi>Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kingham</hi> his Grace, in the Iſle of <hi>Ree.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The killing of the Baſe Brother of the <hi>French</hi> King, at the new Fort before <hi>Rochell</hi> with a <hi>Shott from one of our Ships.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And alſo, The appointed place of Randeuous of the great Fleete Threatned from Forraine parts to <hi>raiſe the Siedge at the Iſle of</hi> Ree.</p>
            <p>With many other particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Walkley,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the Signe of the <hi>Eagle</hi> and <hi>Childe</hi> in <hi>Britaines Burſe,</hi> 1627.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:27994:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27994:3"/>
            <head>A true and moſt exact relation of the taking of the goodly Ship called the <hi>Saint Eſprit,</hi> belonging vnto the <hi>French King, by Sir</hi> SACVILE TREVER Knight, the 28. of <hi>September</hi> 1627.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>French</hi> reſoluing to build ſome Ships for the ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their Nauy, and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting materialls, and Shippe-wrights in the Kingdome, they determined to build them in <hi>Holland,</hi> at <hi>Amſterdame</hi> and <hi>Enchuſen,</hi> a thing which the States of the Vnited Prouinces could not deny them, (it being at their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per coſte) in reſpect of thoſe obligements which binde them to that Nation.</p>
            <p>The notice whereof, together with their ſuppoſed time of Launching, being aduerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into <hi>England,</hi> His Maieſtie to cruſh this Crocodile in the Shell, and to preuent the ſtorme of the danger before it fell, ſent out Sir <hi>Sacville Treuer,</hi> after his returne from the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of <hi>Elve,</hi> where he made the <hi>Haumburgers</hi> come to reaſon, and ſearched their Shipps in deſpight of all oppoſition.</p>
            <p>He had with him in this laſt expedition a Fleet of eight Saile, whereof foure were of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:27994:4"/>
Kings Nauy Royall, the reſt were Merchants.</p>
            <p>His Commiſſion inioyned him to ply vp and downe vpon the Coaſt of <hi>Holland,</hi> and to take all <hi>French</hi> Shipps which he could meete withall.</p>
            <p>He obſeruing carefully theſe Orders, vſed al poſsible ſpeede, and on Friday the eight and twentieth of <hi>September,</hi> he arriued at the <hi>Tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell</hi> (a great Roade in <hi>North-Holland</hi>) about 8. of the Clocke at night, with all his Fleete in ſafety.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The names of his Ships were theſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Kings good Ship called the <hi>Aſſurance,</hi> carrying 38. Peeces of Braſſe Ordnance, wherein Sir <hi>Sackuille</hi> himſelfe went as Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</p>
            <p>The Kings good Ship called the <hi>Aduenture,</hi> carrying 26. Braſſe Peeces, wherein Captain <hi>George Allen</hi> commanded as Vize Admirall.</p>
            <p>The good Shippe called the <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> carrying 18. Peeces of Iron Ordnance, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Captaine <hi>Iohn Pette</hi> the Reare Admirall of the Fleete commanded.</p>
            <p>The Kings good Ship called the St. <hi>Marie</hi> of <hi>Roane,</hi> carrying ſixteene great Peeces, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides murderers, the Captaine whereof was Captaine <hi>Thomas Bardeſey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Captaine <hi>Cheineyes</hi> Shippe called the <hi>May flower of London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:27994:4"/>Captaine <hi>Hookes</hi> Shippe called the <hi>Lyon of Ipſwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Captaine <hi>Morgans</hi> Ship called the <hi>Iacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Captaine <hi>Neadham</hi> a Pinnace belonging to the King, called the <hi>Maria,</hi> carrying ſixe Pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Braſſe Ordnance.</p>
            <p>Theſe foure latter Shipps were of no great burthen, but were well manned, and of quick Steerage, and carried in all, beſides the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers which they had vpon their vpper decks, twenty pieces of Braſſe and Iron Ordnance.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Sackuille Treuer</hi> got a <hi>Dutch</hi> Pilot vpon the Coaſt, who being demanded concerning the Ships that lay in the <hi>Texell,</hi> tolde him, that beſides ſixteene <hi>Hollandiſh</hi> men of Warre and diuerſe other Veſſells of good burthen, their lay one goodly <hi>French</hi> Shipp called the <hi>Saint Eſprit,</hi> which was of the burthen of 800 Tunnes, the vpper works whereof are richly guilt with double Angell Golde in the inſide and outſide of her, in thoſe places which were fitteſt to expreſſe pompe and ſtatelineſſe, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the very Port-holes were curiouſly carued with Lyons heads gaping that were richly double guilt.</p>
            <p>The Pilot after hee had bene fully queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Sir <hi>Sackuile Treuer</hi> concerning al parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars which might tend to the Seruice, tolde him, that if he would giue him him Gold, he would bring him to the ſide of her: whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:27994:5"/>
Sir <hi>Sackuile</hi> gaue him a double <hi>Portugue</hi> in golde, valuing foure pounds ſterling.</p>
            <p>We comming neere vnto their <hi>French</hi> Ship preſently ſhe ſent out her long Boat being manned with <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> to hale vs, and to ſee what we were: But our Admirall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the men to come aboard vs, wee ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed the Long-boate, and pinioned the men and put them in the Hold.</p>
            <p>Afterwards the <hi>Eſprit</hi> diſcouering vs to bee Enemies, began to fight, and diſcharged (but without any effects of hurt) three great Shot and one hundred ſmall ſhot. Then ſir <hi>Sackuille Treuer</hi> being willing to take occaſion by the foretop, and to ſlacke no time for feare of loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing aduantage, came vp cloſe to her, and gaue her a whole broade ſide: ſo likewiſe did our Vize Admirall and Rere Admirall, and the St. <hi>Marie,</hi> where Captaine <hi>Thomas Bardeſey</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded: which Shotte was diſcharged with that quicke motion, and working aduantage, that their maine Maſte and Bowe-ſprit being pierc'd thorough, they cryed out for Quarter, which for good conſiderations was graunted them: ſo that by ten of the clocke at night, which was two houres after our comming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Texel, we became Maſters of this great and warlike Ship.</p>
            <p>Before wee came vp cloſe to her, but after they had diſcouered vs to be Enemies, thoſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:27994:5"/>
of the St. <hi>Eſprit,</hi> made a traine in a Cheſt filled with Gunpowder and other combuſtible ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terialls, to blowe vp the Ship and our men that ſhould enter it. But this reſolution was again altered, becauſe their long Boat being taken by our Admirall, they ſawe no other meanes of eſcape, but onely by ſubmitting themſelues vnto our mercie.</p>
            <p>That night we diſpoſed of her men ſeueral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in our Ships, being one hundred French and fiftie Dutch. We gaue all faire quarter to the Dutch, but the French were kept Priſoners vntil the day before we came out of the <hi>Texel,</hi> and then they were all ſet on land in North Holland.</p>
            <p>After wee had taken this Ship, there came vnto vs Captaine <hi>Dupper</hi> in the <hi>true Loue of Ipſwich,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Wall</hi> in the <hi>Suſan</hi> of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough,</hi> on the Sunday following, whom we welcommed after the manner of the ſea.</p>
            <p>There was another goodly French Shippe, which was newly come ouer Wearing Flatts diſtant eight miles from the <hi>Texel,</hi> who recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing intelligence of our ſtrength, and of what we had done, got Hoyes, Lighters, and other ſmall Veſſels of tranſportation; in which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing lighted her ſelfe of her Ordnance, ſhe got ouer the Flats to <hi>Enchuſen,</hi> before our men could come vp to her.</p>
            <p>Wee came vp with eight ſaile of Shippes to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:27994:6"/>
take her, but looſing our labour, by meanes that ſhe was ſafely harboured in <hi>Enchuiſen,</hi> we returned backe againe vnto our <hi>Admirall,</hi> who expected our comming in the <hi>Texel</hi> roade.</p>
            <p>Some of the States of the neighbour towns, came aboard vs, and demaunded peremptori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by vertue of what commiſſion we came to fetch that Ship out of their Rode. Our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall tolde them, that he had commiſsion to take all French Ships, which hee could meete withall, and hee was aſſured that this was a French Ship, and therefore hee aduentured to take her without any further commiſsion.</p>
            <p>Cap. <hi>George Allen</hi> our Vize Admiral &amp; ſome others of this Fleete, ſtayes vpon the coaſt of Holland, for the intercepting of this and other French Ships: the reſt vnder the conduct of Sir <hi>Sackuill Treuer</hi> brought home the ſurpriſed Ship to <hi>Harwich.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This goodly Ship taken on the 28. of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember, as is aforeſaid, had 42. Peeces of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance mounted, twelue Peeces vnmounted in her hold, 2006. Armours, one hundred and fifty Muskets, and 60. barrels of Gunpowder.</p>
            <p>The ſpecification of her Ordnance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:27994:6"/>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>ITem, vpon her lower Tier</hi> 20. <hi>whole Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerings of Braſſe of full ſize, being in height fiue inches and a quarter.</hi> 20</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>In her ſtearage two demie Culuerings of Braſſe, in height foure inches, one quarter, and better.</hi> 2</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Item, two Drakes vpon the halfe decko, being braſſe of Sacker bore.</hi> 2</item>
                  <item>24. Braſſe.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Item, vpon her vpper Tyer</hi> 12. <hi>Dema-Culuerings of Iron in height, foure inches and a quarter:</hi> 12</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Item, foure Sackers of Iron vpon the halfe decke.</hi> 2</item>
                  <item>18. Iron.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Summe totall mounted is 42.</p>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>ITem, it is reported there is in hold twelue Peeces of Iron, all whole Culuerings, wee
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:27994:7"/>
tooke the height of two, being fiue inches, the rest we could not come to. <hi>12</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The length of the Shippe by the keele, is <hi>105.</hi> foote: <hi>105</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The breadth by her beame is <hi>35.</hi> foote. <hi>35</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>From the Kilchin to the Deck in depth twelue foote. <hi>12</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Item, <hi>2006.</hi> Armours.</item>
                  <item>Item, <hi>150.</hi> Muskets:</item>
                  <item>Item, <hi>60:</hi> Barrels of Gunpowder:</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:27994:7"/>COncerning the proceedings of our Armie and Nauie in the Iland of <hi>Ree</hi> (commonly called Saint <hi>Martins</hi>) there hath happened no memorable accident, as farre as we can vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, ſince the Wedneſday ſennight after Sir <hi>Iohn Burrowes</hi> was ſlaine, vpon the night of which day our men ſurprized diuers Boats as they were paſsing to the Fort with Victualls: the particulars of which exploite were related in our laſt Iournall: but concerning the occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences happening in the Maine, we haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued their aduertiſements by Letters out of <hi>France</hi> on Wedneſday laſt being the third of October.</p>
            <p>That the French King being fully bent to follow his Deſignes againſt <hi>Rochell,</hi> and to plucke out that thorne, which (as the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall intimated vnto him) had ſo long ſtucke in the ſides of his Soueraigntie, continues the building of his new Fort, of purpoſe to debar the Townes-men from all ingreſſe and egreſſe by water. He followes this worke with great charge and greater labour, as well knowing how important the finiſhing thereof will bee for his farther ends and intentions. Hee hath cauſed twelue whole Cannons to be mounted before the breaſt of this Fort, with which his Canoniers make diuers randome ſhot into the Towne, but with more terrour then danger.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:27994:8"/>
Some Ships of our Fleet riding not farre from the Fort, haue beſtowed diuers ſhot vpon the French, though without point blanke diſtance. One of which fell ſo fortunately for vs, and ſo vnfortunately for them, that it killed a baſe ſonne of that great <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, which he had by a ſiſter of the Duke of <hi>Orleance.</hi> The ſame ſhot did likewiſe kill another Duke, of whoſe name wee are not as yet certaine. And the wind of that bullet ſtruck downe the Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur (the legitimate Brother of the French King) as hee was conferring with the other two.</p>
            <p>It is further confirmed that two principall men of the French Nobility were ſlaine by the late Ambuſh of the <hi>Rochellers.</hi> Which two Noblemen with diuers other braue Cheua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liers, were drawne within danger by a ſtale made by twenty common Souldiers in the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite of Gentlemen, who ſallyed forth of the Towne of <hi>Rochell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Rochellers</hi> are very carefull to furniſh our Fleete and Armie, with all neceſſarie Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſions, which their ſtore or procuration can afford: and theſe they tranſport in twenty long Boates, which in token of the ſeruice that they owe vnto the King of <hi>England,</hi> carrie red croſſes for the deuice of their colours. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Engliſh who haue beene either ſicke or wounded are in the Towne, amongſt whom is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:27994:8"/>
that honourable Knight Sir <hi>Charles Rich,</hi> who is cured of his wound, but hath not as yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered the perfect vſe of his arme. His pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is much deſired of my Lord <hi>Duke,</hi> and is expected in the Armie euery day.</p>
            <p>His Excellencie to auoyde the extortion of Victuallers, who like the milt in mans body growe fat by the leaneneſſe of others, hath out of his Noble diſpoſition publiſhed a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation for the price of Bread, Wine, and other neceſſaries, according to the rates of which Proclamation, the Ilanders and others from the Continent doe bring in Victualls.</p>
            <p>There is a confident report in all thoſe parts of <hi>France,</hi> that there are appointed ſorty Ships of Warre to come from <hi>Spaine,</hi> and twenty from <hi>Dunkerke,</hi> who are to ioyne with the French Fleete for the ſuccours of the Iland, and the beating off of the Engliſh. The Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuowe of all theſe Shippes was appointed at <hi>Blawet,</hi> a famous Port Towne in <hi>Brittanie,</hi> on the tenth of this preſent moneth.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
